A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Economic Development and Administration, Office Files FA1551
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Economic Development and Administration, Office Files
1950-1967
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1551
4.3 Cubic Feet 11 boxes (10 letter document containers and 1 legal document container)
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 and was ingested by the RAC as part of Accession 2019:012 (boxes 30255, 30256, 30358); 2019:028 (box 30254).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series:
1. General Files, 1950-1967
2. Fellowship Files, 1956-1964
The original order of the material was maintained.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
In 1950, the Ford Foundation's Trustees planned out five areas of activity. One area, Program Area III, revolved around "activities designed to advance the economic well-being of people everywhere and to improve economic institutions for the better realization of democratic goals." To comply with the Trustee's recommendations, the Foundation created an advisory group composed of leading economists. They published their report in 1954 with recommendations to focus on four major problem areas in the field of economics: 1.) understanding the effects of private interests of businesses, government agencies, labor unions, and other organizations on public welfare; 2.) maintaining economic growth and stability; 3.) improving private and public policy; 4.) improving international economic relations. The economists proposed the Foundation focus on funding research activities, development of personnel in the field, and educating the public on economic issues.
In the 1950s and '60s, the Ford Foundation followed the advisory group's recommendations by funding conferences, nonprofits, and universities in the studies of natural resources, manpower, economic development, international economic relations, and the improvement of business administration and performance. The Foundation also funded faculty and student fellowships in economic studies, research centers at universities, and provided grants to improve business education at the undergraduate and graduate level.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the formative documents of the Ford Foundation's program in Economic Development and Administration, including the meeting materials and correspondence of the initial advisory group. The collection also holds memos, reports, grant proposals, fellowship files, and budget information pertaining to initiatives to improve education and research in the fields of business and economics. The collection spans from 1950-1967.
Business education; Economic development; Fellowship programs; Ford Foundation
- General Files, 1950-1967; 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains documents related to the development of the Ford Foundation's Economic Development and Administration program. This includes correspondence and meeting materials from the advisory group commissioned to shape the program, Foundation staff files (Kermit Gordon, Oscar Harkavy, Neil Chamberlain, Martin Shubik, Marshall Robinson), reports and surveys related to graduate studies in business and economics, and reports related to research centers at universities and the role of computers in economics education.
  - Advisory Group: Working Paper and Comments, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Consultants: Ideas, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes 'Meetings of Consultants to Program in Economic Development and Administration, 29 September 1956'
  - Advisory Group: Executive Committee Meeting, 1953 November 24 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Advisory Group: Executive Committee Meeting, 1953 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Advisory Group: Meeting, 1953 December 4-5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Advisory Group: Meeting, 1953 October 16-17 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Advisory Group: Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Advisory Group: Other Documents, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Program Development, 1950-1962 (Box 1, Folder 9-10, Box 2, Folder 11-16)
  - Consultants Meeting, 1955 December 9 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Experts, 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Bootstrap Appropriation, 1958 September (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Multiphase Appropriation, 1958 March (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Questionnaires and Accompanying Letters to Graduate Foreign Business Students, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Training for Teachers of Business Administration in Underdeveloped Countries, 1960 April 4 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - The "Economics of Change" Meeting, 1961 June 16 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Business Games as Research Devices L60-65, 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Report of Evaluating Committee on Resources for the Future, 1963 February (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Authors: Harrison Browne, Robert McNee, Peter Odegard (Chairman), Theodore Schultz
  - Grants - Economic Development and Administration - Categorical Breakdown, 1957-1964 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Grants and Projects - Status Reports, 1962-1965 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Status Reports, 1958-1961 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - A Plan for the Continuing Study of the Activities of Federal Regulatory Agencies, David F. Cavers, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Economic Development Business Program Summary, 1958 December (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Program in Economic Development and Administration Staff Memos - Victor Fuchs, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Program in Economic Development and Administration Staff Memos - General Program, 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Economic Development and Administration - Interoffice Memos, 1959-1963 (Box 3, Folder 33, Box 4, Folder 34-37)
  - Neil W. Chamberlain - Speeches, 1959 November 19 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Program in Economic Development and Administration Staff Memos - Allan Carter, 1957-1959 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Program Planning Budget, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Kermit Gordon, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Staff Memos - D.W. O'Connell, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Special Programs, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Staff Memos - Neil W. Chamberlain, 1958-1959 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Staff Memos - Oscar Harkavy, 1957-1960 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - First Interim Report Ad Hoc Committee on Special Programs, Neil W. Chamberlain, The Ford Foundation, 1959 June 15 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Neil W. Chamberlain - Ad Hoc Committee on Special Programs, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Neil W. Chamberlain - Committee on Puerto Rico, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Ad Hoc Committee - Economic Cooperation for Growth and Freedom, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Kermit Gordon - Continental Classroom, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Possible Projects in Puerto Rico, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Kermit Gordon - Notes on European Trip, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Martin Shubik - Correspondence Regarding Computers, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Martin Shubik - Ptd. and Mineo. Material - Reports and Articles on Computers and Higher Education/Industry, 1959-1961 (Box 6, Folder 54-55)
  - Martin Shubik - Trip Reports, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Computer Reports and Articles, 1958-1960 (Box 6, Folder 57-58)
  - R. Ruggles - Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - G. L. Bach - Notes, Memos, and Report Drafts, 1959-1961 (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - Health and Education - General Correspondence and Data, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - Government Economic Policy - General Correspondence and Data, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Government Economic Policy - Proposals, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Institution Building - General Correspondence and Data, 1964-1966 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Background Memo to Heald on Long-term General Support of Institutions, 1964 September 11 (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Brookings Institution - Ford Foundation Staff Work on Endowment, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Institution - National Bureau - Working Notes - Support M. Robinson, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Institution Building - Survey Research Center - University of Michigan (F. Mann), 1962-1965 (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - International Business and Economics - Latin America - Correspondence and Data, 1964-1967 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Latin America - Report of Mission to Explore the Feasibility of an Institute of Advanced Administration, Calkins, Jeuck, 1964 July 3 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - The Social Sciences in Latin America Conference, Rio de Janeiro (G. L. Bach Attended), 1965 March 29-31 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Latin America - ESAN (Stanford University's Graduate School of Business in Lima, Peru), 1964 (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Economic, Education, and Research - Proposals, 1964-1966 (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Economic Education - National Opinion Research Center (NORC) Evaluation of "College of the Air Course: The American Economy", 1964 (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Economic Education - Seminars in Economics for Law Students (J. Dunlop-Harvard), 1966 (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Southern Methodist University - An Economic Information and Services System Feasibility Study (David Ott), 1964 (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - Economic Research - Case Institute of Technology - Research in Industrial Economics (B. Gold), 1966 (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Economic Growth - Correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Economic Growth - General Correspondence and Data, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - Marshall A. Robinson - Meeting with Kingsley Davis and Peter Murdock, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Business Education - General Comments on Programs, Etc., 1958-1965 (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - American Association of Collegiate Schools of Business, 1954-1964 (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Economic Growth - Proposals, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - Economic Growth - National Industrial Conference Board (NICB) Survey of Businessmen, 1963 May (Box 8, Folder 84-85)
  - Economic Performance in Government - Brookings Conference, Reestablishing Program to Aid States and Local Governments Strengthen Financial Structure, 1965 May 19 (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - Columbia County, Maryland - Establishing Graduate School of Public Service (R. Landrum), 1966 (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - Correspondence Regarding Grant Proposals - Marshall Robinson, 1964-1966 (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - General Correspondence and Data, 1964-1966 (Box 8, Folder 89)
    Correspondence with Ford Foundation staff, including William Pendleton and Marshall Robinson; as well as reports related to proposals
  - Manpower - Social Science Research Council - "Interrelations of Manpower, Population, and Economic Change," Paul Webbink, 1966 June (Box 8, Folder 90)
  - Manpower - Pending Proposal Letter, 1964 April 14 (Box 8, Folder 91)
  - Manpower - General Correspondence and Data, 1964-1966 (Box 8, Folder 92)
  - Inter-University Consortium for Political Research - Survey Research Center, University of Michigan, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 93)
  - Endowment Grant - Survey Research Center - Inter-University Consortium for Political Research - Second Annual Report, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 94)
    Sections include: Summer Program, Data Repository, Membership, Related, and Staff and Budgets
  - Institute for Social Research, 1946-1961, The University of Michigan (Publication) (Box 8, Folder 95)
  - Important Business and Economic Education - List of Professors with Interest and Competence in Latin American Business Administration (Submitted by Ernest C. Arbuckle), 1964 (Box 8, Folder 96)
  - Monterrey Institute - Report by Howard Jeuck, Robinson - On the Proposal, 1965 January (Box 8, Folder 97)
  - Publicity - Summer Workshops (at Business Schools), 1964-1965 (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - Summer Workshops for Business School Faculty - Correspondence and Data, 1962-1964 (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - International Economics Studies in American Universities - Correspondence, 1955-1958 (Box 9, Folder 100-101)
  - International Economics Studies in American Universities - Review of University Courses, 1956-1957 (Box 9, Folder 102)
    Yale University
    University of Wisconsin
    University of Washington
    Stanford University
    Princeton University
    Northwestern University
    Massachusetts Institute of Technology
    Johns Hopkins University
    Harvard University
    Cornell University
    University of Chicago
    Columbia University
    University of California (Berkeley)
  - International Economics Studies in American Universities - Campus Visits, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 103)
  - Publicity - Summer Workshops, 1958-1963 (Box 9, Folder 104-105)
    Includes pamphlets from participating universities, applications, correspondence, participants list, etc.
  - Federal Government Activities Related to Ford Foundation, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 106)
  - Fluid Research Funds, 1955-1961 (Box 10, Folder 107)
  - Industrial Engineering as Related to Business Administration, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 108)
  - Social Science Applications to Business, 1960-1961 (Box 10, Folder 109)
  - Computer Program Planning Memos - Correspondence and Data, 1959-1963 (Box 10, Folder 110)
  - Economic Growth - Behavioral Sciences Division, National Research Council - Preparation of Volume on Current State of Knowledge in Social Sciences (K. Davis, P. Murdock), 1964 (Box 10, Folder 111)
  - Top Twenty-Five American Universities Receiving Largest Amount from Ford Foundation, 1950-1964 (Box 10, Folder 112)
  - Economics Growth - Planning, Memos, Proposals, Data, 1962-1963 (Box 10, Folder 113)
  - Preparation by Herbert Morton of Booklet on Economic Development and Administration, 1964-1966 (Box 10, Folder 114)
  - Industrial Relations Roundtable, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 115)
  - Transportation, 1964-1965 (Box 10, Folder 116)
    Includes report - Motor Metropolis: Some Observations on Urban Transportation in America by Edgar M. Hoover and correspondence
  - University of Pittsburgh - Proposal to Establish Colombian Management Science Center, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 117)
  - Public Administration, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 118-119)
- Fellowship Files, 1956-1964; 2
  In a 1954 report, an advisory group of leading economists and business administrators recommended the Ford Foundation fund fellowships in economics and administration to develop strong personnel in the field. The first fellowships were awarded in 1956.
  This series includes memos, grant action forms, fellowship terms, press materials, application forms, form letters, survey materials, correspondence, spreadsheets, and lists of fellowship recipients. The types of fellowships awarded include: predoctoral fellowships, faculty research fellowships, faculty study fellowships, and doctoral dissertation fellowships in economics and business.
  - Results, 1961-1962 (Box 10, Folder 120)
    Spreadsheets - Predoctoral Renewals, Faculty Research Fellowships, Faculty Study Fellowships, Predoctoral Fellowships, Doctoral Dissertation Fellowships
  - Results, 1962-1963 (Box 10, Folder 121)
    Doctoral Dissertation Fellowships, Faculty Study Fellowships, Doctoral Fellowships in the Social Sciences for Dissertations on Business, Predoctoral Fellowships, Predoctoral Renewals, Faculty Research Fellowships for Social Science Research on Business, Faculty Research Fellowships
  - Fellowship Forms Books, 1956-1964 (Box 10, Folder 122, Box 11, Folder 123-126, Box 12, Folder 127-131)